Guide to the Eoin McKiernan and Deirdre McKiernan Hetzler Papers AIA.081
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Eoin McKiernan and Deirdre McKiernan Hetzler Papers
1917-2014
1947-2010
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
McKiernan, John Thomas, 1915-2004
Hetzler, Deirdre McKiernan
AIA.081
14.75 Linear Feet in 7 record cartons, 5 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize flat boxes, 3 oversize folders, and 2 folders in shared housing
25 audiocassettes
1 videocassette
8 Reels
11 DVD-R
24.7 Megabytes in 238 computer files.
Eoin McKiernan (1915-2004) was a scholar of Irish Studies in the United States (US) and the co-founder in 1962 of the Irish American Cultural Institute (IACI) in St. Paul, Minnesota. He led the effort to revive and preserve Irish culture and language in the US. The Eoin McKiernan and Deirdre McKiernan Hetzler Papers date between 1917 and 2014, with the bulk of the materials dating between 1947 and 2010. The collection consists of McKiernan's personal papers, records of the IACI, and material documenting Deirdre McKiernan Hetzler's work on her biography of her father, Irish America Reawakening: The Eoin McKiernan Story. Materials include McKiernan's personal correspondence, writings, and production material for Irish Diary, a public television series he wrote and hosted in the 1960s; business records from his involvement in the IACI; and the Irish America Reawakening material, which includes Hetzler's correspondence, research materials, legal documents regarding her Freedom of Information Act requests, and galleys of the book.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Researchers interested in using audiovisual materials in this collection (films, cassette tapes, VHS tapes, et cetera) must use a digitized copy, which we refer to as an access copy. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room; materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. These requests are free of charge and can be made in anticipation of your visit. The process typically takes four to six weeks. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A librarian will respond to you with further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The majority of the collection was donated by Deirdre McKiernan Hetzler in April 2016, with additional accessions in July 2016 and June 2018. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2016.040, 2016.041, 2018.107, and 2018.120.
In March 2025, Marion Casey donated an accretion of an event program and speech; the accession number associated with this transfer is 2025.030.
Appraisal
The majority of Eoin McKiernan's research files consisted of clippings from newspapers and magazines and were removed.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series: Series I. Eoin McKiernan Papers, Series II. Irish American Cultural Institute Records, and Series III. Deirdre McKiernan Hetzler Research Materials. Each series is arranged in alphabetical order by format, name of person or organization, or title of work.
Biographical Note
Eoin McKiernan (1915-2004) was an Irish Studies scholar, teacher, and founder of the Irish American Cultural Institute (IACI). He was born John Thomas McKiernan, but adopted the old Irish form of his name early in life. He was a professor of English at the State University of New York at Geneseo (1949-1959) and at the University of St. Thomas in St. Paul, Minnesota (1959-1972). He retired from education in 1972 to dedicate himself full time the IACI. He dedicated his career to reviving and preserving Irish culture and language in the United States.
Deirdre McKiernan Hetzler was born in 1940 and is a member of the national board of the IACI and has served as the chair of the Rochester, New York Chapter of the IACI. She was a Campus Minister at St. John Fisher College in Rochester.
Scope and Contents
The Eoin McKiernan and Deirdre McKiernan Hetzler Papers date between 1917 and 2014, with the bulk of the materials dating between 1947 and 2010. The collection consists of McKiernan's personal papers, his records of involvement with the Irish American Cultural Institute (IACI), and material documenting Deirdre McKiernan Hetzler's work on a biography of her father, Irish America Reawakening: The Eoin McKiernan Story. McKiernan's personal papers date from 1917 to 2006, with the bulk between 1947 and 2000, and include personal correspondence; drafts and published versions of his writings; his research files; scrapbooks; and scripts, notes, photographs, slides, and recordings of Irish Diary, a public television series he hosted in the 1960s. Roughly half of McKiernan's correspondence is in Irish, with other material in Irish throughout the collection. Material from his IACI involvement dates between 1964 and 2005 and includes correspondence, reports, minutes, memoranda, and issues of Dúċas, the organization's bi-monthly publication. The Hetzler material dates from 1953 to 2014, with the bulk dating between 2005 and 2010, and includes correspondence, research materials, legal documents regarding her Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests, and galleys for Irish America Reawakening.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Custodial History
The collection was packed by Deirdre McKiernan Hetzler. The majority of the collection was donated by Hetzler in April 2016, with an additional accession in July 2016.
Related Materials
For more information on the Irish American Cultural Institute, see the Irish American Cultural Institute Records at the University of St. Thomas Archives & Manuscripts Collections.
Irish language -- History -- 20th century.; Irish Americans -- Societies, etc.; Irish Americans -- Biography; Correspondence.; Documentary television programs.; business records; Photographs.; Irish newspapers.; Irish American Cultural Institute; Grace, Princess of Monaco, 1929-1982
- Series I. Eoin McKiernan Papers, 1917-2006; 1947-2000; 9 Linear Feet in 3 and a half record cartons, 2 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize flat boxes, and 2 folders in shared housing; 1 videocassette; 11 DVD-R; 5 audiocassettes; 3 film reels
  Scope and Contents
  This series documents McKiernan's interest in Irish culture and language, his work to revive American interest in these areas, and other aspects of his personal life. Material dates from 1917 to 2006, with the bulk between 1947 and 2000, and includes his personal correspondence, half of which is in Irish; drafts and published versions of his writings on Irish culture, language, and history; his notes and research files; scrapbooks; and material used in the production of three television series on Ireland. McKiernan's correspondents include Brian Friel, Henry Beston, Mairead Nic Dhonnchadha, and Liam Eise. His notes, research files, and writings show his interest in Irish language and history, particularly the events of the 20th century as relates to the formation of the Republic and the conflict in Northern Ireland. His interest in the Irish language is documented through a small collection of early 20th century Irish language newspapers, including An Lóċrann, Fáinne An Lae, and An Gaedeal. The scrapbooks document McKiernan's work as an educator and with the Irish American Cultural Institution and include correspondence, photographs, newspaper clippings, and event ephemera. The three television series McKiernan wrote and narrated in the 1960s, Ireland: The Past in the Present, Ireland Rediscovered, and Irish Diary, are included in this series. Materials related to these titles include scripts, photographs, slides, and correspondence. Other material in this series includes awards received by McKiernan, photographs of him, and interviews he gave on radio.
  - Awards and honors, 1959-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1, Box 15, Cassette 1, Dvd 1-3, Box Shared Tamiment 193, Folder 6)
  - Biographical materials, 1947-1999 (Box 1, Folder 2, Box 12, Folder 7, Box 13, Folder 11-13)
  - Biographies, 1973-2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence -- A-Ba, 1959-1966, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence -- Beston, Henry, 1947-1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence -- Between, 1990-1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence -- C-D, 1941-1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence -- Eise, Líam, 1947-1951, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence -- Friel, Brian, 1969-1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence -- F-He, 1959-1998 (Box 1, Folder 10, Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence -- Hubbell, Lucy Embury, 1949-1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence -- I-Ne, 1948-2000 (Box 1, Folder 12, Box Shared Tamiment AIAOS001, Folder 3, Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence -- Nic Dhonnchadha, Mairéad, 1940-1989 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Correspondence -- O-W, 1957-2000 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence -- War Resisters League, 1943-1947 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence -- Unknown, 1956-2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Curricula vitae, 1969-1995 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Easter Rising films, 1960 (Box 9, Reel 1-2, Box Shared Tamiment 030, Folder 6)
  - Education records, 1947-1957 (Box 1, Folder 19, Box Shared Tamiment AIAOS001, Folder 3)
  - Employment records, 1949-1993 (Box 1, Folder 20, Box 8, Cassette 1)
  - Funeral, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Guthrie Lecture, 1978 (Box 8, Cassette 25)
  - Interviews, 1979-1983 (Box 8, Cassette 2-4)
  - Irish Educational Services, 1994-2006 (Box 1, Folder 22, Box 12, Folder 9-10)
  - Irish Famine Curriculum Committee & Education Fund, Inc., 1995-2000 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - Irish language newsletters, 1954-1962 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Irish language newspapers, 1917-1935 (Box Shared Tamiment 031, Folder 12-19)
  - Notebooks, 1935, 1959-1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
  - Notes, 1947-1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 28-31, Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Photographs, 1950-2002 (Box 1, Folder 32, Box Shared Tamiment 030, Folder 7, Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Research files -- Doherty, Joe, 1989 (Box Shared Tamiment 030, Folder 8)
  - Research files -- General, 1922-1999 (Box Shared Tamiment 030, Folder 9, Box 12, Folder 1-3, Box 13, Folder 9-10, Folder 14, Folder 16)
  - Research files -- Irish Republican Army, 1931-1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Research files -- MacBride, Sean, 1985-1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Research files -- McGarrity, Joseph, 1940, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Research files -- McKiernan, Jeannette, 1935-1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbooks, 1968-1973 (Box 10, Box 11, Box Shared Tamiment 031, Folder 20, Box Shared Tamiment 008, Folder 6)
  - 1798 Commemoration, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 5-6)
  - Speeches, 1951-1995, undated (Box 1, Folder 33-35, Box Shared Tamiment 193, Folder 7)
  - Television series -- Ireland: The Past in the Present, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
  - Television series -- Ireland Rediscovered, 1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 8-13, Box 15, Dvd 6-11)
  - Television series -- Irish Diary, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Box 15, Dvd 4-5, Box 2, Folder 14-27, Box 4, Folder 1-7)
  - Writings, 1947-1997 (Box 4, Folder 8-12, Box Shared Tamiment AIAOS001, Folder 2, Box 12, Folder 11)
- Series II. Irish American Cultural Institute Records, 1964-2005; 2 Linear Feet in 1 and a half record cartons, 1 manuscript box, and 1 oversize folder.
  This series documents McKiernan's involvement in the Irish American Cultural Institute (IACI). Material dates between 1964 and 2005 and includes correspondence; reports; minutes; memoranda; issues of Dúċas, the organization's bi-monthly publication; photographs; pamphlets; and a film of an IACI event attended by Princess Grace of Monaco, who served as the institute's honorary International Chairperson between 1972 and 1982. Included in this series are materials documenting McKiernan's work on IACI programs including Irish Fortnight, a series of lectures given by Irish academics over the course of two or three weeks across the United States; tours of Ireland, including the Irish Way; and Trees for Ireland, a reforestation program that established several forests in Ireland. Also included is correspondence between McKiernan and Princess Grace, photographs of them together at IACI and other events, and clippings about her involvement with IACI and her death in 1982.
  Historical note
  The Irish American Cultural Institute (IACI) was founded in 1962 in St. Paul, Minnesota by Eoin McKiernan, Jeannette McKiernan, and Patrick Butler. The institute's mission is to promote the study of Irish culture, serve as a patron for Irish cultural endeavors, and stimulate Irish cultural development.
  - Agenda, 1966-1994, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Articles of incorporation, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - American Irish Foundation, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Annual report, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Awards dinner, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Balance sheets and earning statements, 1967-1980 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Board meeting packet, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Boardletter, 1980-1990 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Budgets, 1987-1990 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Bylaws, 1981-1988 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Celtic News Service, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Chapternotes, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Chapters, 1983-1987 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1964-2001 (Box 4, Folder 26-32, Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Corporate membership packet, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Directors, 1968-1984 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Dúċas, 1972-2005 (Box 5, Folder 5-7, Box Shared Tamiment AIAOS001, Folder 1)
  - Éamon de Valera Memorial Endowment, 1974-1976 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Éire-Ireland, 1969, 1988, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Endowed research funds, 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Ephemera, 1966-1996, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Evening of Achievement Honoring Dr. Eoin McKiernan, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Events, 1975-1986 (Box 5, Folder 13, Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Film of event attended by Princess Grace of Monaco, undated; cuid197 (Reel 17, Reel 18, Box Shared Tamiment 127, Reel 16)
  - Financial statements, 1975-1993 (Box 5, Folder 14-15)
  - Ireland tours, 1973-1985 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Irish American Cultural Institute Development Fund, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Irish American Cultural Institute film, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Irish American Cultural Institute News, 1986-1991 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Irish American Cultural Institute poetry and literature awards, 1971-1990 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Irish American Information Service, 1992-2000 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Irish Fortnight, 1974-1987 (Box 5, Folder 22, Box Shared Tamiment AIAOS001, Folder 1)
  - Irish Perceptions, 1983-2001, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Irish Way, 1978-1996 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Job descriptions, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Member mailings, 1972-1989 (Box 13, Folder 17, Box 14, Folder 1-9)
  - Memoranda, 1966-1994 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Minutes, 1972-1991 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - National Council, 1971-1974 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1973-1984 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Newsletters, 1974, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Notes, 1986, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Operational and committee structures, 1968, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Organizational histories, 1987, undated (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Photographs, 1977-1999, undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Press releases, 1968-1973, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Princess Grace of Monaco, 1973-1985 (Box 12, Folder 12-16, Box 13, Folder 1-6)
  - Proposals, 1978, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Reports, 1978-1994, undated (Box 6, Folder 3-5)
  - Speeches, 1971-1982 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Trees for Ireland, 1984-1990 (Box 6, Folder 7, Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Victory Dinner, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 8, Box 8, Cassette 5-6)
- Series III. Deirdre McKiernan Hetzler Research Materials, 1953-2014; 2005-2010; 1.5 Linear Feet in 1 record carton and 1 manuscript box.; 24.5 Megabytes in 238 computer files.; 20 audiocassettes
  This series documents Deirdre McKiernan Hetzler's research and work on a biography of Eoin McKiernan, Irish America Reawakening: The Eoin McKiernan Story. Material dates from 1953 to 2014, with the bulk between 2005 and 2010, and includes paper and born-digital materials, including correspondence between Hetzler and McKiernan's friends and colleagues; interviews with McKiernan's friends and colleagues; research materials; and publication materials for Irish America Reawakening, including galley proofs and publicity materials. This series also includes Hetzler's Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests, legal cases resulting from these requests, and copies of the material she received from the Federal Bureau of Investigation and the Department of Education. The research material includes original correspondence between McKiernan and Riobard Mac Góráin and Pádraig Ó Mathúna, dating between 1953 and 2002.
  - Correspondence, 1973, 1990-2014
    - Paper Materials (Box 6, Folder 9-11)
    - Digital Materials, TW_AIA_081_ER_2
  - Freedom of Information Act requests, 1990-2012
    - Paper Materials (Box 6, Folder 12-21)
    - Digital Materials, TW_AIA_081_ER_1
  - Interviews, 2005-2008, undated
    - Audio Materials (Box 8, Audiocassette 7-24)
    - Digital Materials, TW_AIA_081_ER_6
  - Notes, 2005, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Publication materials -- Author biography, 2008; TW_AIA_081_ER_4
  - Publication materials -- Book launch, 2013-2014
    - Paper Materials (Box Shared Tamiment 031, Folder 21)
    - Digital Materials, TW_AIA_081_ER_7
  - Publication materials -- Book synopses, 2008-2012; TW_AIA_081_ER_8
  - Publication materials -- Galley proofs, 2012 (Box 6, Folder 22-23)
  - Publication materials -- Press releases, 2012-2014; TW_AIA_081_ER_5
  - Research materials -- General, 1953-2009, undated
    - Paper Materials (Box 6, Folder 25-27, Box 7, Folder 1, Box Shared Tamiment 030, Folder 20)
    - Digital Materials, TW_AIA_081_ER_3
  - Research materials -- Mac Góráin, Riobard, 1970-1990 (Box 7, Folder 2-5)
  - Research materials -- Ó Mathúna, Pádraig, 1967-2014 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)